Okay, let's wait a few minutes till we
have
uh few more than 100 people.
Wait
a few seconds.
All right, folks. Let me begin. It's
6:31. Uh, we're going to continue with
our series on training neural networks.
This is the last lecture in the series.
So, here's a quick recap where we left
off. We know that we train neural
networks by minimizing minimizing a loss
function which quantifies the gap
between the output of the network and
the desired output of the network.
The uh this loss function is a function
of only the network parameters. Can you
guys hear me?
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes, we hear you.
>> Yes, we Yes. So, all right. Uh so this
loss function is a function of only the
network parameters
and we minimize it through gradient
descent
which are iterative updates against the
gradient of the loss with respect to the
parameters. We saw in the last class
that batch updates must process the
entire training data before each update.
Whereas incremental update algorithms
like SGD and mini batch updates speed it
up by updating using random individual
inputs or subsets of inputs.
And these are faster to converge but
they have greater variance. Trend
algorithms smooth out variations and
incremental update methods by
considering long-term trends and
gradients and their variance. And this
can lead to faster and better
convergence. That was the last thing we
saw. So moving on, the topics for the
day, we going to cover a whole bunch of
things. We're going to look at
generalizations, divergences,
normalizations, dropout, and a few other
tricks.
So here's the setup again. When we train
neural networks by gradient descent, the
loss is the average divergence
between the actual output of the network
and the desired output of the network
computed over all the training samples.
And this loss is a function of all of
the network parameters.
The convergence of the gradient descent
depends on how good this divergence
function is. Now what were the
properties that the divergence function
uh was supposed to have? Can anybody
remind me what properties was the was
the divergence function supposed to
have?
Anyone?
Anybody?
It should be differentiable. What else?
What else?
We stated a few things, right? that it's
zero when both inputs are the same and
it's always positive. Right? There are
lots of functions which have the same
same uh these two properties but they
can have entirely different shapes.
Ideally the divergence function must
have a shape that results in a
significant gradient in the right
direction outside the optimum so that it
guides the algorithm to the right
solution. So for example, if you have if
the x-axis in each case is a network
parameter and the y-axis is the
divergence. If you have a divergence
function like the one to the left, do
you think this is good? Is that a good
divergence function that that you would
be able to optimize? The one on the
left?
What about the one in the middle?
Is this a good one? No. What about the
one to the right, extreme right? Is that
a good one?
So why is the one to the extreme right
better than the one in the middle? Both
of them are smooth. Both of them have
nice clear minima.
So why is the one to the extreme right?
Uh better
anybody?
Someone want to take a guess?
Steep slope at the minimum, right? Low
slopes far. So if you have something
like this bowl over here which is flat
far away and very steep near the optimum
then your gradient descent whose step
depends on the derivative is going to be
very slow far away from the optimum. And
then when it approaches the optimum
because this the the
function is steep the steps are going to
be large and it's very likely to just
bounce out of the minimum and have a lot
of difficulty getting to the minimum.
Whereas the function to the right, this
slope is large far away and small closer
to the minimum. And so you would take
large steps far away and small careful
steps closer to the minimum. So the
function to the right is clearly better
than the one to the left.
That making sense to everybody.
Yes.
Okay. And so
uh what is this bouncing in terms of
functional? I'm not sure what exactly
you mean by that. But then these are the
iterations of gradient descent and the
step size. The step is dependent on the
derivative. So out here the derivative
would be large. So you're going to take
a large step. You'd end up here. The
derivative is larger. Still you take a
large step and go right out. So these
are not very good functions.
So what are good choices for divergences
for in for regression problems where
you're trying to predict a continuous
varied variable. A good divergence is
the L2 divergence. If you're trying to
predict a scalar output, then the L2 jar
divergence as we define it as half of
the actual output minus the desired
output whole squ. Now the half as a
matter of convenience so that when you
take a derivative the two that comes out
here cancels out the two. when you're
trying to predict many many outputs a
vector of outputs then two you would use
the L2 divergence for regression
problems except now the L2 divergence is
going to be half of the sum over all
components of the square of the
difference between the actual and
desired outputs of the network. If
you're trying to perform classification
then we saw we prefer using the KL
divergence which is defined like so. If
you're trying to predict a single binary
value minus d log y - 1 - d log 1 - y
and why did we say this made sense? What
was the reason for choosing this uh uh
divergence? Anybody?
Why did what was the reason for uh
choosing this divergence here?
Does anybody remember?
So why not use the RMSSE? The RMSSE just
put a root.
Yeah, it doesn't really change except
make the derivatives a little muggly. It
gives probability but it's not just that
that you would have probability but if
your desired output matches the true
output
the divergence is zero. But if the
desired output does not match the true
output. So the desired output is one and
the and the actual output is zero then
this is infinitely wrong. Or if the
desired output is zero and the actual
output is one, this is infinitely law
wrong. And the kale divergence has this
property. So it captures the spirit of
classification in some sense.
Now when you're trying to perform
multiclass classification
you'd have a softmax layer which outputs
a probability vector and here too you'd
have the kl divergence which is uh the
sum over all classes of d log d minus d
log y. If you use a one hot
representation for the desired output
this first term goes away and you're
just left with minus of the log of the
probability of the target class. We've
seen this in
Now, what's stopping us from using the
L2
for classification problems?
Here's what suppose I'm trying to
perform a binary classification problem.
The target output one or zero, right?
So, or here, let's say my target output
is 0.5. Then my kale divergence you will
see goes up to in infinity at zero and
infinity at one and is minimum at 0.5.
The L2 divergence doesn't quite go to
infinity. It goes to 0.25 on both sides
but it's nice and bold shaped. Are both
of them convex?
What do you think? Are both of them
convex?
Yes or no?
Yes. Okay. Which of them seems like the
nicer function?
Which one seems like the nicer function?
L2. Right? But then here is the crazy
bit. When you actually
uh have a neural network, you're going
to have some inputs. The network
computes something. Let's see. Why don't
Okay, the network.
Oh well, the network computes some
output and then you get a a fine value
and then
that aine value goes through a soft max
and then you get the probabilities Y.
You get the desired output D and you
compute the
KL divergence between these two guys.
But then the divergence you could take
the derivative of the divergence with
respect to y. You could also take the
derivative of the divergence with
respect to the z right which is below uh
which is the input to the soft max.
Is this is this making sense what I'm
saying over here that the derivative of
the divergence could be taken with
respect to both y and z. Let's look at
how those derivatives behave. So when I
take the derivative with respect to Z,
here is the derivative with respect to Z
for the KL divergence. Here is the
derivative with respect to Z for the L2
divergence. Which of them is convex?
Now which looks nicer, right? The K
looks nicer, does it not? And so it
happens that when you go through uh ugly
nonlinearities
then uh you have this property that what
looks nice and convex early can end up
looking really ugly later. What looks
like a not so nice function can end up
looking convex. And in this case we find
that the KL divergence is actually
better when you think of the derivative
with respect to the input to the softmax
than the L2 divergence. So besides the
nice probabilistic represent
interpretation the kale divergence also
has this property that it's actually
nicer for classification problems which
is why we use scale. This is when uh I
have a uh network. If if I have two
parameters, let's say if I'm just
performing a classification on a two
dimensional feature, then
if I computed the L2 divergence between
the output of the network and the
desired output and computed the
derivative with respect to say the two
parameters. So let's say I have W1 and
W2 and then I have my softmax and it's
making a prediction. So within the
softmax you first comput a Z out here,
right? And then you you get an output Y
and then you compute a divergence. If I
compute the derivative of this
divergence with respect to Y,
>> the L2 is going to be nice and yes.
Uh so the L2 is going to be nice and
bullshaped. The KL is going to be
something like this. But then when you
look at the derivatives with respect to
W1 and W2,
then the L2 divergence actually looks
like this flower which is not convex
whereas the KL divergence looks like a
nice nice bowl. So to answer the
question about who is EG freedom M
please have your names right.
And we always have an activation on the
final layer for classification. The
activation just happens to be implicitly
the softmax.
And we just since the since the class
that PyTorch has gives you the
derivative with respect to Z, you don't
actually have to ex explicitly write the
softmax code because uh what the heck is
this?
uh
you don't have to explicitly write the
softmax code because it's in there and
it just gives you the derivative.
So L2 divergence is not convex with
respect to network parameters to the
final softmax parameters whereas scale
divergence is although both of them have
a unique global minimum. So
there is no activation activation after
after the softmax. Your final layer is
going to look like this, right? You're
going to have the embeddings your Z and
then you have a linear layer over here.
If you're writing code, you're just
using this linear layer and passing it
to the loss function. But inside the
loss function, there's actually a
softmax that's being computed. But you
just don't see it because if because
this the way pytor has been written you
actually get the derivative with respect
to the z rather than with respect to the
y.
That answer your question Thomas.
So
all right any questions on that?
Yes. So I'm assuming that that went
through right. And the nice thing about
computing the derivative with respect to
Z is that for regression problems, the
derivative just ends up being Y minus D,
which is the error between the actual
and the desired outputs. And regression
problems, you don't have an activation.
For classification problems too, the
derivative just ends up being Y minus D,
where Y is the output of the softmax and
D is the desired output. So again as you
can see this y requires a soft max
although you may not see it but this is
the derivative with respect to z and so
in both cases the derivative with
respect to z is the error and this is
the error we propagate backwards which
is why the method uh back propagation is
sometimes called error back propagation.
Did all of this make sense? Any
questions?
Any questions? Yes. No.
Okay, there are no questions. Okay, did
this make sense? Give me a yes or no
like
four or five yeses
considering there are almost 200 people
in class. I'd expect to see more. All
right, so that said, here is your first
poem.
Okay, 10 seconds, guys.
end the poll right here.
Okay. Does anybody want to answer the
first question? Which of the two is
convex with respect to the weights of
the final softmax layer?
Anyone? Which of the two?
K. Right. For the most popular networks,
regression network with linear layer
using L2 loss and classification network
with softmax output and cross entropy
loss. What is the gradient with respect
to the final final afine value Z?
What is it? It's just going to be
this, right? This is what we said. Which
is what makes the KL so nice for
classification. Perfect. You got it.
Now, so the story so far, we've also
seen gradient descent can be sped up by
incremental updates. Convergence can be
improved by smooth updates. What we've
added now is that the choice of
divergence affects both the learn
network and the results.
We'll move on to another problem.
Training with many batches makes a
fundamental assumption.
What is this assumption?
What is the assumption that uh training
with mini batches makes? Anybody?
Anyone?
We said this uh in the last class but uh
maybe I didn't make it explicit. Uniform
variance no when we train with mini
batches we are assuming that all the
mini batches have very similar
distribution and that they are capturing
the overall distribution of the data. In
reality each mini batches can have a
very different distribution what is
called a coariance coariant shift. And
in fact this shift can be very large and
this will affect training badly and
particularly because the neural network
is a nonlinear
uh uh function right as you go through
the layers
if I have two mini batches which are
very close in this layer by the by the
by the time they come out to this layer
they can end up in two very different
places simply because small changes in
the input can result and large changes
in the output in highly nonlinear
functions. And so you have this
phenomenon where all the mini batches
can be in different places. And this
kind of violates our basic assumption
that all the mini batches have very
similar distribution. So what can we do?
We can add some extra processing that
moves all the mini batches to a standard
location in the space. So that after e
every time like I said each layer could
potentially move all the mini batches to
different directions. So you add some
more processing here so that they end up
being similar. Maybe the next layer does
it all over again and moves them all to
different locations. Then you can add
this processing once more and bring them
back to the same place. And so this ends
up being uh very beneficial when you
want to train your model. And this is
what is called batch normalization. Did
the principle make sense to everybody?
Yes or no?
Right? So
how do we do this? Right? We want to
move all the batches to a standard
location of the space. But where to
determine this? We're going to do a
two-step process. First, we are going to
move all the batches, mini batches
individually to have a mean of zero and
a unit standard deviation. How do you
move a batch of data to have zero mean?
How is this done? Can anybody tell me?
How is the batch move to have zero mean?
Anyone?
You just subtract the mean of the data.
You compute the mean of this batch,
subtract it, the mean becomes zero, and
now the batch is centered at zero. How
do you make it unit variance
afterwards?
How do you make it unit variance?
you divide by the standard deviation,
right? So you're going to do X minus
mean of the mini batch and divided by
the standard deviation and this will uh
move the mini batch to zero. So that's
what we're going to do. Each mini batch
is first going to be moved to the origin
and then
every single mini batch is going to be
moved to a fixed location in the space
location unknown. And now if we have
this extra processing, every mini batch
regardless of where it started off from
is going to end up over here. Which
means now they all have very similar
distributions. And then you can have the
rest of the uh network operate on uh
operate on data which follow our basic
assumption. So
assuming all of that made sense, here is
our second property.
15 seconds, guys.
Okay, let me stop the poll.
What is the answer here?
It's going to be many batches, right?
Easy. That's what we do. Very good. So,
where do we have this batch
normalization process? Usually the batch
normalization process can be put
anywhere. Typically as it was first
defined uh we
for every layer in every neuron you
first compute an aphine value and then
put it through an activation. Right? So
the batch normalization as originally
proposed was performed on the aine value
of all of the uh all of the neurons. So
how is it done?
The neuron just takes a bunch of inputs
and then first computes an aphine value
which as we all know is just the uh
weighted sum of the inputs plus a bias
right and then this guy you're going to
operate on all of the mini the entire
mini batch and then first compute the
mean of the mini batch. This is for a
mini batch. So you'll be these are all
the Z values for the
Professor,
looks like we lost him.
She might log back in.
Can you still hear?
>> Uh, yes. You cut out a bit, but we can
hear
you're muted.
Can you hear me now? Can you hear me
now?
>> Yes, there's an echo.
This should be better, right? All right.
Sorry about that. My network just
barfed. I have exciting things going on
at home. So, uh, just picking up where I
left off. Why do we think we're
computing this mean and this variance?
Anyone
for the mini batch?
Why do we compute it?
Can someone please respond?
Normalization.
Normalize. So remember what we said that
we first want to move all the data to
the center. Right? To move it to the
center, we need to subtract the mean and
divide by the standard deviation. And so
in the first step, we're going to
compute the mean and the standard
deviation. Subsequently, you're going to
compute the normalized term and this
normalized term subtracts the mean and
divides by the standard deviation. This
epsilon over here is just meant to
ensure that we don't have uh uh you know
this to account for under for very low
variance. In case the variance is zero,
you don't you don't end up with a divide
by zero. Right? So this step
actually perform this performs this
operation which moves all the data into
the central location. Now from here at
this point all the data have zero mean
and they have unit variance. If I want
to move it to this location with some
other spread what would I have to do to
move it from here to here? I need to
perform two steps. What are they? Can
someone tell me?
What would I need to do? I have the
normalized var variable u
someone.
What would I need to do?
First I'm going to multiply by the sigma
over here. Correct? So that it becomes
the right size. Then I'm I'm going to
add the new mean
which is this location over here. And
that's going to move the entire thing
out here. Right? So that's exactly what
we will do. We're going to
first normalize
the data mini batch by subtracting the
mean and dividing by the standard
deviation. Then you multiply by the
gamma which is the new standard
deviation and add a beta which is the
new position which is and this is going
to be done individually for you each
unit in the network each neuron in the
network. I can write the whole thing
like Z goes through a step little box
which first computes this the normalized
version and then there's a second box
which comprises of multiplying by gamma
and adding a beta which gives you the Z
hat in the new position.
So this normalizes the mini batch. So is
this clear to everybody what we done
what we've done so far?
Yes. Okay. So this unfortunately adds
some problems. What is that? In the
standard assumption we assume that in a
mini batch all the instances were
independent of one another. So when I
computed the derivative of the mini
batch with respect to any network
parameter, I just had to compute the
derivative of the divergences for the
individual instances with respect to W.
Can I still do this when I do batch
normalization? What do you think? Can I
do this when I do batch normalization?
Yes or no?
What do you guys think?
One guess. No. Why not?
Well, so no idea. Here's why. Right. I
like the honesty. Because the output of
the network of any neuron is a function
of the mean and the variance of the mini
batch. Remember every data instance is
being normalized and this is the mean
and the v the mean and the variance of
the mini batch. So this means that the
divergence for any single training
instance depends on the z values for the
rest of the mini batch which all influ
influenced mean and the mean and
variance. If I were to write this, so if
I were to write this out, if these are
all the Z's of the mini batch, they all
operate together to compute the
normalized and shifted Z hats for all
the mini batch. Modifying any one of
these Z's will modify all of these guys
because modifying the Z will modify the
mean and the variance. And so you have
this, if I were to draw this out more
carefully, right? This is what it's
going to look like. These are all the
Z's of the mini batch. So I've drawn the
influence diagram just as before.
All of the Z's
influence the mean. Right? Every one of
these Z's influence the mean. Every one
of these Z's and the mean influence the
variance. And then when I try to compute
the normalized version of any Z, that's
going to be dependent on not just Z, but
also the mean and the variance. And so
that means this hue depends directly on
Z but also depends on all of these Z's
through the mean and the variance. Did
that make sense?
Yes or no? Right? And so computing
derivatives is no longer a trivial
thing. It actually becomes somewhat
tedious. It's not difficult. So when I'm
going backwards over here, I can always
compute the derivative of the loss with
respect to the normalized U. Easy enough
because the derivative with respect to u
is simply going to be the derivative
with respect to z times the derivative
of this act activation function. No big
deal. I can compute the derivatives with
respect for a whole bunch of things like
uh uh here again are all the terms. I
compute the mean of the mini batch the
variance. I normalize each instance and
then I shift it. when I'm going
backwards I can compute the derivative
with respect to back propagation is
going to give me the derivative with
respect to y already right so this is
given so to move the derivative back
here all I need to do is to multiply the
derivative with respect to y with by the
derivative of the activation function no
biggie so at that point I have the
derivative with respect to the
normalized and shifted version of D
then sub subsequently I have to go back
I need to compute the derivative with
respect to again the new position and
the new standard deviation are learned
right so the new position is beta the
new standard deviation is gamma so I
need derivatives with respect to gamma
and beta what I already have the
derivative of the loss with respect to
zhat so what is the derivative with
respect to gamma anybody from this
formula what is The derivative with
respect to gamma,
what's it going to be?
The derivative of the loss with respect
to gamma
that's
the derivative of the loss with respect
to gamma simply going to be dl over dz
hat * ui. Right?
Yes or no?
What is the derivative with respect to
beta?
What would it be
guys? That's just going to be dl over dz
hat. And so and so easy enough. We know
how to compute the derivatives for the
term parameters here. We can also take a
step backwards. Those are those, right?
Then I can take a step backwards and
compute the derivative with respect to u
which is exactly the same formula as
before. So it's a derivative with
respect to z hat times
gamma right. So that this this function
2 comes directly of this formula.
So at this point we have the derivative
with respect to u and we have the
derivatives with respect to the
parameters for the shift. So is
everybody good with me so far? Is all of
this clear? Because now we go into the
slightly more tedious math, right?
So we just trying to we don't want to
keep it at zero. We don't know what is
representative what is the most optimal
position position. So we learn it if
that uh optimal position happens to be
around zero. So far so good right again
Iet why do we do batch normalization
again we spend the entire first few
slides explaining this. Rightet
I think you join 20 minutes late.
That's why you don't join 20 minutes
late. You're going to ask questions that
have been answered, right?
Please be on time like a quarter of your
joint between 15 and 20 minutes late.
It's not acceptable, right? So
uh okay.
So at this point we have the derivatives
with respect to u.
What do we do next? We want to go back
and compute the derivatives of the loss
with respect to these Z's, right?
But that has to consider this
complicated influence diagram. How does
that make things complicate things?
Let's take a look. And before that, we
have our third poll.
10 seconds, guys.
Okay, let me end this poem.
Okay. What is the answer to the uh
Bruno? That's okay. You can answer me
here. What's the answer to the first
question?
Which which which statements are true?
So, which statements are one, right? And
in the second question, which of the
statements are true?
Which two? Okay. In batch norm, the
normalized due for any Z depends on all
the other Z's in the mini batch. And so
it's actually a vector operation which
takes a bunch of data and produces a
bunch of outputs. This makes things
complex. So let's see how here is the
normalization stage of batch. Now it
takes a whole bunch of Z's produces a
whole bunch of U's. If I want to compute
the derivative of the loss with respect
to any Z, if you look at the influence,
each Z influences every U, right,
through this horrible network over here,
influence picture. And so, and all of
these U's eventually influence the loss.
So if I want to get the derivative of
the loss with respect to Z, any Z, I'd
have to sum over all of these U's and
the and the term at sum is the product
of the derivative of the loss with
respect to that U times the derivative
of the U with respect to Z. So is this
equation making sense to all of you?
Yes or no?
Is this making sense? Okay. So that
means I mean the derivative of the loss
with respect to U is already computed.
This term must be computed for the for
every J pair. Meaning you need to
compute the derivative of every U with
respect to every J. And that's ugly. So
let's see how that works. First let's
consider the through line. The U that's
derived from a Z. I'm taking Z1 as an
example. The corresponding U is U1. What
are all the dependencies?
How does E u depend on Z? There is the
through line. So the derivative of U
with respect to V1 with respect to Z1 is
going to be have one part through this
direct connection which is the partial
of U over Z. Then the second is there a
second connection over here between U
and Z Z Z Z Z Z Z Z Z Z Z Z Z Z Z Z Z Z
Z Z Z and U can you guys point out
what's the second one
second path from Z to U in this network?
Anybody?
You go that there's this guy right Z
influences mu mu influences u so I have
to add the der the derivative of u with
respect to z through this path which is
du over d mu * d mu / dz right is there
a third path
this guy right it goes through the
variance so for this I need the
derivative of u with respect to sigma
time the derivative of sigma squ* the
derivative of sigma square with respect
to z. So we'd have to work this math
out. Now let's see how this works out.
Right? First consider the derivative of
u with respect to z through the straight
path. For the straight path we're going
to have to use this connection. Right?
This path. What is the derivative of u
with respect to z through this formula?
Anybody?
What is the derivative of U with S? Is
it one? What is it
again? What's the derivative of U with
respect to Z, guys?
1 / square root of variance, right? So
that's going to be this guy.
One over square root of variance.
The second. So we've got this first guy
done. Let's look at the second one.
Right. The second one. There's the first
term. What is what is the derivative of
U with respect to mu? Mub again using
the formula because this is the formula
that links you in -1 / root again right
is just -1 / square root. Perfect. So
let me plug that in. What is the
derivative of mu with respect to z?
Again mu has been obtained from this
formula here. Right? What is the
derivative of mu with respect to z?
Right?
So we haven't yet got to sigma John. So
what is that's just one over b. Right?
Let me plug that in here. And so
beautiful. We have the first two terms.
Now there's the third term. Right? What
is the derivative of u with respect to
sigma squared?
Anybody?
What is the derivative of u with respect
to sigma squ?
That's easy enough.
If I have
>> 1 / in general if I have 1 / say square
roo of sigma squ plus epsilon this
is simply sigma 2 + epsilon
raised to - 1 / 2. So if I take the
derivative of this with respect to
sigma^ 2 this is going to be sigma^ 2 +
epsilon raised to - 3 /2*
-1 /2
right is that correct
is this right or am I missing something
right so if this is what it is then uh
here's what I will have this term is
just going to be
and then don't forget
uh that's you have zus mu on the
numerator right so it's minus z - mu b /
2 * sigma^ 2 + epsil - 3 /2 so is
everybody happy with the formula here
yes or no
okay was not hard right so let me plug
that in here Right? That leaves me with
this guy sigma squar with respect to z.
Sigma square connects to z through these
two paths. Right? So if I want the
derivative of sigma square with respect
to z, how many terms will it have?
Anybody?
If I want the derivative of sigma square
with respect to z, how many terms will
it have? Two. It's going to be this
direct path sigma squar with respect to
z. And the second path which is sigma
square with respect to mu time mu with
respect to z. So if I work it out what
is this first guy I'm going to use this
formula here.
What is the derivative of sigma squ with
respect to z from this guy here?
What is it guys? Anyone?
Very simple.
is just going to be
indeed you have sigma square is just
going to be 2 * z - mu b
correct
so
we have got this guy right that leaves
us with the second term let's consider
the first derivative the first one is
sigma squar with respect to mub right
what is the derivative of sigma square
with respect to mu B from this formula
what is it
anyone? What is it?
It's going to be this is over the entire
mini batch right? So it's going to be
different. And it's going to be like so
sigma derivative of sigma square with
respect to mu is 1 / b summation over
all the instances of - 2 *
z / mu. Do you agree with this formula?
Is this right?
Yes or no?
Okay. Now let's work it out. Right. So I
can just move this minus2 out. It's -2
over b summation over the any b entire
mini batch z minus mu. What is this?
What is this term going to be? What is
the sum
of all the instances after they have
been after the mean is subtracted? What
is the this term going to be? Anybody?
What will this be?
Anyone?
That's just going to be zero, right?
Which means the sigma squar derivative
of sigma squar with respect to mean the
mean is going to be zero. This term is
zero. So I can ignore this. Which means
the derivative of sigma square with
respect to z is just 2 * z minus mu / b.
So let that let me plug that in here.
And so here is the overall form for the
derivative of the true line. Now it
looks very tedious, but do you think was
the math hard? What do you think?
Was the math hard or was it? It was
easy, right? Once you understand how
it's done, it's easy. So, uh, so it how
is it zero? Basically, because when I
when I uh take the summation of Z minus
mu, there's going to be summation z
minus. So, I've just pulled the 1 / b
over here. It's 1 / b summation z minus
1 / b summation mu, right? And this is
just the mean.
This is 1 / b * b * the mean. It just
becomes zero. Okay? But in any case,
when you have a centered data set, the
average of all the data data instances
is zero. So we have this very easy
formula. That's for the straight line.
So this is the derivative for the
through line, right? Uh the uh for the
cross line. Again,
now we have two paths, right? one
through the mu,
the other through the sigma. And if you
work out the derivatives, this is very
similar to the through line, except that
it's missing this one direct connection.
And so if you work out the arithmetic,
it's just going to come out to be very
similar. This the one through the mu is
going to give you 1 - 1 / b * roo
of sigma square. and the one through the
sigma squar is going to give you minus z
minus mu z i - mu * z j - mu because the
derivative of the i u with respect to
the j / b *
sigma^ 2 raised to 3 /2 so did this
formula make sense as well I haven't
derived it but you guys think you can
derive this
right
so again that's because the mean is the
sum of all the instances, isn't it?
So, you're going to take the derivative
of Z with respect to mu. Mu with respect
to Z, but the new is a sum of all the
instances. That answer your question?
I'm assuming it did, right?
So, here you have it. Very the math is
easy. I'm rushing a bit because I lost a
few minutes due to my internet. So,
here's the overall derivative of U.J J
with respect to ZI. If J equals I, it's
this three-term derivative. If J is not
equal to I, it's this two-term
derivative. We already derived it. The
complete derivative of the loss with
respect to any Z is going to be summing
over all the U's of the pro and the of
the the sum is of the product of the
derivative of loss the loss with respect
to U times the derivative of U with
respect to Z
and the derivative of U with respect to
Z of course we saw was given by this
formula right combining them all I'm
just writing the math I'm not going to
work it out because I think you you
you'd get it easily enough the math
makes sense Right? So that's going to
give you this crazy
uh formula. This first term which only
exists for the through term is going to
give you 1 / sigma square root of sigma
square the derivative of the loss with
respect to ui. The second term which is
present for both the direct and ind the
direct and indirect terms where J equals
I and J is not equal to I that's going
to give you - 1 / B * the roo of
sigma 2 times the sum over all the U's
of the derivative of the loss with
respect to U. And then you have this
third term which I can combine and say
uh this is minus zi minus mu^ 2 this is
minus z i minus mu zj minus mu I take
the common zi term out I take the
denominator out so I have minus z i - mu
divided by b * sigma^ 2 ra to 3 /2 and
then the sum over all the j's one of is
going the d of the derivative of the
loss with respect to uj*
zj minus mu V. So this formula shouldn't
be hard to comprehend
from these guys. Do you think do you
guys think you can believe this formula?
Yes or no? I'm not asking you to
understand it, but you think do you
think you can believe it?
Okay.
And there's something interesting that
comes out of this. Right? So here is the
whole thing. But now look at this. Let
me consider a mini batch where all the
training data instances are identical.
If all the training data instances are
identical, then I'm going to say d loss
over dui
is simply going to be d loss over du for
all the training data instances. Yes. Is
that right?
Yes or no?
Okay. What happens to these first two
guys in that case? What happens to these
first two guys?
This first term is going to give you 1 /
roo of sigma squ and we'll skip the
epsilon just for convenience dl / du.
The second term is going to give you
minus 1 / b*
1 / roo of sigma 2 summation
dl / du.
Because all of these are identical, the
summation simply becomes B * DL / DU.
So this B will cancel out this B in the
denominator. And so you're going to end
up with 1 / sigma 2 DL / DU
minus 1 / roo of sigma 2 DL / DU
and these two will cancel out and they
become zero. So this term becomes zero.
Can you see that?
Yes or no? Right.
Okay. And what about the second term?
What happens here?
Once again, this d loss over duj is the
same for all of them. So this comes out
of the summation. I can write this as d
loss over du
time summation
z minus mu. Right?
What is summation z minus mu?
What is summation z minus mu over the
mini batch? Zero. This two becomes zero.
And so you have this in situation where
if all the instances in the mini batch
are identical, then the derivative of
the loss with respect to the u to the z
simply becomes zero. So here's our final
pole.
10 seconds, guys.
Okay,
stop this right here.
What is the answer?
True or false?
True. Right. So if all the instances are
mean the mini batch are are identical or
very similar then batch normalization
simply blocks the bra gradient
computation going backwards and back
propagation will fail.
So batch normalization only works when
the training data and the data in the
mini batch are sufficiently diverse.
So that's for training. But during
inference you're actually
during training you work with mini
batches. So the mini batch has a mean
and a variance. Where do we get this
mean and variance for from during
inference where you're processing data
one instance at a time. So it turns out
that for that all we do once the model
has been fully trained is to compute a a
a mean of all the means of the mini
batches and that's going to be the
global mini batch mean. Similarly, you
compute the average of all of the
variances of all the mini batches and
that's going to be your global uh mini
batch variance. And you'll be using
these guys
in your uh during inference.
So did did this make sense? Why this is
even an issue? And the solution here
during training you have many batches.
So you can actually compute a mean and a
variance. During inference you have only
one instance. It doesn't have a mini
batch mean or a mini batch variance. So
but you still need the batch
normalization stage. So for that the
mean that you use is the average of the
batch of the means of all the mini
batches and the variance is the average
of the variances of all the mini batches
that make sense
okay and so we will move on right and
batch normalization you can apply
typically it's applied between Z and on
the Z's but you can apply them after the
activation you can apply them to some
layers but not the others and not the
others. But then as I explained early
on, it makes more sense when you apply
batch normalization after every layer
because nonlinear layers tend to uh move
the mini batches out away from each
other and bringing them back to be close
to one another really helps. And so here
was the results from the first paper on
batch normalization by EF and Zedi. And
this was I think on uh I don't remember
the task but this dotted line is your
standard training model. I think it was
imageet and then when they apply batch
norm various kinds of batch norm you can
see how it converges so much faster and
to a much better solution and that's
because it has batch norm has this prop
property of bringing all these scattered
mini batches back together to to enhance
the training. So any questions about
batch null?
Any questions? Yes. No.
Okay, I'm assuming. So, did this make
sense? Give me a thumbs up and I'll move
on.
All right, I got one thumbs up floating
up my screen. There you go. Right. So,
the story so far, we just add that
coariant shift between training mini
batches may cause problems, but this can
be handled by batch. Now,
but there are other issues.
The figures that we showed, they were
all sort of assuming that the data were
well specified. You had enough training
data. In reality, your training data are
going to be very sparse. We're trying to
learn to attempt to learn an entire
function from just a few snapshots of
it. Right? So, we compute a loss, which
is the average error between the true
and the desired output of the network at
all of these training data points.
And we minimize this loss. But there's
nothing stopping the network from
learning a function such as this which
merely fits the training data points and
completely misses the function you want
everywhere else.
So this making sense
the issue here yes or no.
So, okay, I see one thumbs up. Can I see
a few more? Okay, so one second.
So,
how do we fix this? We need an
additional smoothing constraint that
will fill in the missing regions
acceptably, right?
So, to explain how we get this, let's
look at a simple binary classifier
that's been trained on these red and
blue dots. Your ideal network is going
to compute something like this smooth
function. But there's because the
network is an universal approximator,
there's absolutely nothing stopping the
network from learning this crazy purple
function.
Is this making sense to you guys that
the network could end up learning the
purple function rather than the blue
one? Yes or no? Right. So, how do we
prevent this?
the pre to prevent this we have to go
back and look at why this can be learned
and this can only be learned because the
perceptrons in the network are
individually capable of very sharp
changes in the output here is a standard
perceptron if I'm using like a a
logistic or a softmax output uh the the
the uh basically the sigmoid for
instance the sigmoid has this 1 / e to
minus wx as The formula
for small values of W, the sigmoid is
going to be smooth like so.
As W keeps increasing,
when we when W is infinity, the sigmoid
actually becomes a perfect step
function. And so as W keeps increasing,
the sigmoid can get steeper and steeper
and steeper. And if you allow the
sigmoid to get arbitrarily steep then
the network can end up learning this
function instead of the smooth function
that we want.
This making sense to everybody?
Yes or no?
So how would you prevent this? How would
you prevent this?
Anyone
suggestion for how you would prevent
this label smoothing? Now, how would you
prevent this?
Don't let W get too large because if W
gets large, this can get very steep. So,
you're going to say, I'm not going to
let W get so large that the function
gets steeper than this one. So, we put a
restriction on W. And when you put a
restriction on W, the individual
perceptrons end up being smooth. And
that will prevent the learning of this
function. That make sense to everybody?
Yes or no?
Okay. So, we're going to constrain the
W's.
And the way we will do it, here's your
standard loss function. But to the
standard loss function, now I'm going to
add the squared norm of the weights
themselves. And so, this one minimizes
the loss. The second term ensures that
the W's don't get too large. So,
is this making sense? Our solution here,
what the second term is doing, it's
making sure that the W's don't get too
large because you're going to minimize
the loss. You're also minimizing the
W's. Right?
Let's take the derivative. If I take the
derivative of this guy, that's going to
be just the standard derivative, you
know, average of the gradients. But the
second term is simply going to give you
lambda times w. Right? This has come
from the second term. When I plug it
into your standard gradient descent
rule, this is going to be w minus 1 / *
this one here which comes from the first
term
>> and the second term which comes from
this one. This guy comes from this one.
That make sense to everybody.
Is this making sense to everybody?
Yeah. And let's move things around,
right? I can So when I put this in my
gradient descent formula, this first
term is from the standard derivative.
The second is this guy which came from
your regularizer. Let me merge these two
terms. If I write ATA* lambda as beta,
that just ends up being the update rule
says that I'm going to be multiplying W
by some 1 minus beta and then applying
the gradient update.
Is this making sense
that when you try to keep the W small,
you end up with this formula? Yes or no?
I see one here. one beta is simply a
time I just use beta as as a shortcut
for this
that make sense
to everybody
right there's one yes from so is this
formula familiar
if you've been going through your
homeworks what was that what is this
Guys,
anybody? What is this?
Someone. Okay. Where did I lose you in
this?
Where did I lose you in this?
You're multiplying the weights by a term
which shrinks it. This was your
weight
decay, right?
Yes or no?
Right.
I have three very reluctant yeses. What
about the rest of you guys? Did I lose
you?
Okay. So what weight decay does is to
implicitly is actually a mechanism for
ensuring that the weight themselves are
small by including the squared norm of
the weights in your loss function and
then when you use that in your gradient
descent you end up with weight decay.
Okay.
So in your actual pseudo code in the
update rules after computing the
derivatives you'd be multiplying the
current weights by by a factor that's
slightly less than one before you apply
a correction. And this ensures that the
weights don't get too large.
But then there's another way of looking
at regularizing. It turns out that if
you have uh any kind of restrictions on
the weights, then
each layer of the network tends to
smooth the overall function a little
more. So the first layer may learn a
crazy function like this. The next layer
smooths this guy. The next layer smooths
it further still. So as you make the
network deeper and deeper, the function
it learns gets smoother and smoother. So
here's an example. uh it was a very
simple example where this was done for
me by uh uh Jacob and Pulkit and
Berkeley some years ago. Uh this is a
decision boundary that we're these are
decision boundaries we're trying to
learn. We drew thousand training data
points from both. Then we trained a
large network and applied every training
trick we could know we could think of
and these are the decision boundaries it
learned. Nothing like these guides,
right?
But then let's try trading off depth
versus uh width. So here we're playing
with these two decision boundaries. In
each case we have 660 neurons. If I
arrange them as three layers of 220
neurons here is the decision boundary it
learns. Four layers of 115 neurons. This
is what it learns. Six layers of 110
neurons. This is what it learns. 11
layers of uh of 16 neurons. This is what
it learns. Same thing over here. Right?
So, what is the overall lesson? Take
home take-home lesson from this little
experiment over here. The take-home
lesson over here.
Anybody? What is the take-home lesson?
Anyone else? Mr. Zubima.
Deeper networks are better. How?
Deeper networks apply implicit
regularization on the function and so
are more likely to learn generalizable
functions than shallower ones because of
this behavior. That make sense to
everybody?
Yes or no?
Okay. And so
data under specification can result in
overfitted models and must be handed by
regularization and more constraint
generally in deeper architectures.
One last topic. Uh there have been many
techniques proposed to improve the
regularization.
No Georgina they wouldn't. So the most
influential method so far for
regularization is probably dropout. And
before I introduce dropout here is this
very popular technique for improving the
generalization of machine learning
models in general. So uh it's called
bagging
>> where from the same training data you
draw different subsets of the training
data and learn a classifier from each of
these and then you finally average all
of these classifiers and when you do so
you find out that this overall method is
much more robust and much more accurate
than simply training a single classifier
from all the training data. It's called
bagging proposed by Leo Bryman and uh uh
it's a very successful and popular
method. It has a lot of theoretical
underpinnings as well.
So let's go back to neural networks.
We're going to do something strange
in dropout. During net training for each
input at each iteration, we flip a coin
with a probability of one being 1 minus
alpha. And if the coin comes up with a
one, we retain the neuron. If it comes
up with a zero, we just delete it. So
you might end up after flipping your
coin with a network like this. And what
really happened was that the coin came
up with zero for all of these masked
neurons. And so you were left with the
remaining network. You would do this
separately for each training instance,
which means that each training instance
is going to see a different network.
Also because you do it each time the
same training instance is going to see
different networks in different epochs
and during when and when you're learning
the network if you apply back
propagation back propagation also is
going to go over this reduced network
for each training instance. This process
make sense to all of you what we just
did the procedure.
Yes or no?
rest of you guys. Okay. So
what is the interpretation of this? For
a neural network of this kind with n
neurons, if I create different networks
by switching off different neurons,
there are two race to n possible sub
networks. So what dropout is doing is
effectively sampling over all two race
to n possible networks. It learns a
network that
averages over all possible networks. So
dropout seems to be performing something
very similar to bagging. This is one
statistical interpretation. Another
interpretation is this that when you
have a large network, networks have this
tendency that some layers will simply
learn a pass through. Meaning instead of
learning something useful, this layer
might just learn to copy the input over.
So effectively the layer was rendered
useless because all it did was pass the
data on. If you have dropout sometimes
these neurons are going to get switched
off which means these layers can no
longer learn a pass through. They're
actually going to learn rich meaningful
connections. So this is the other
interpretation for why dropout works.
But the statistical interpretation based
on bagging is what the procedure
actually builds on. Did all of that make
sense?
Yes. No.
Right. Okay.
So, the pseudo code, what does it look
like? Within each layer for each neuron,
you compute a mask by by by
computing a boli variable, which is like
flipping a coin. And the mask is going
to be a one or a zero. Basically,
turning on off different neurons. And
then all the neurons are multiplied by
the mask which determines whether the
neuron is retained or not. During back
propagation, the neurons that were
switched off in the forward pass must
not be passing derivatives going back
either. So we can just use the same mask
that we computed in the forward pass in
the back propagation when you update the
derivatives and use that in the back
propagation. So overall this doesn't
introduce a lot of complexity in the
code. The only extra bit is computing
this mask which is applied both going
forwards and going backwards.
So that's quite right but that's the
training but what about inference?
Now dropout effectively samples over two
to n networks.
So on the if you want to use the
statistical principle of bagging what
you would want to do is to evaluate all
2 to n networks
and average their outputs where the two
to n networks are obtained by switching
different combinations of the neurons
off. So what you really want is the
expected value basically the average of
the outputs of all 2 to n networks. This
will give you your bag output. Is this
making sense to you guys? This one?
Yes. No.
I don't Can I get a few more yeses?
Okay.
Can we actually compute this?
Yes or no?
What do you guys think?
No, because it's order 2 to n. So we
going to use an approximation.
The network is a function of the
individual neurons. Right? So instead of
taking an expectation of a network which
is a function of individual neurons,
we're going to approximate it as a
network of the expectations of the
individual neurons. Do you see that?
This do you see this approximation? It's
not exact. It kind of works. So is this
making sense?
Instead of the average of the networks
of networks,
expectation of networks working on
neurons, we take a network of the
expectations of neurons. Does this make
sense?
Yes. No.
Here's terms. Okay. in any here's a
anytime I do expectation of f ofx for
any function
if this is very complicated and a
standard hack is to take the f of the
expectation of x this is an
approximation that's not accurate this
is an approximation
that made sense for now
let's go so that's basically what you're
doing here. It's an expectation of a
network of network neuron outputs which
is a network of expectation of neuron
outputs. Did that make sense ma'am?
Yes. No.
Right. And so that makes things simple.
Each neuron is actually this guy, right?
and it's actually turned on or off with
a Bernoli variable D which is a
probability of alpha. So the expectation
of a neuron is simply the expected value
of D. And if D is a Bernoli variable
with a probability alpha, the expected
value of D is just alpha. So what we
will do now is that each neuron output
is simply going to be multiplied by
alpha which is the dropout factor.
This make sense?
Yes. No
over here.
Okay. And so that's what we will do when
you actually run the pseudo code. But
then when you run the code instead of
simply during inference instead of
directly using the network output you
multiply by alpha. You can do a few
other things. uh apply applying alpha to
a neuron output is the same as
multiplying the weights coming into a
neuron by alpha. So you can simply
premultiply the weights of all of the
learn network by alpha and use the uh
network with a premultiplied weights
without modifying the activations
or during training you can actually
replace each activation by alpha inverse
sigma which means that during inference
you just you can just use sigma. So
these are all just different ways of
implementing the uh implementing dropout
during inference time. So how does that
work? Turns out that it really really
makes a difference. This is I think from
NEST classification error. This is what
they got without dropout across uh uh
iterations once they use dropout you can
see how much the error falls. Now one of
the issues with dropout so there are
many variations of it. drop out. There's
something called zone out, drop connect,
shake out. Why do all of them are built
on the same basic principle of trying to
create an ensemble of models from a
single model?
So to add add to our story so far,
dropout is a stoastic data model method
that sometimes forces the network to
learn most more robust models. Now one
of the characteristics of dropout is
that dropout famously doesn't work very
well with batch norm. Why does dropout
not work with batch norm? Because in
batch norm within each batch we compute
a variance of the mini batch. And when
you drop things out then the number of
samples in each mini batch changes uh
from node to node in fact because
dropout will be switching off different
neurons. And so the variance estimates
are going to be very noisy for the batch
norm. And so when you combine dropout
and batch norm good things don't always
happen but otherwise it's a great
technique by itself. So we come to the
basically at the end of this there are a
bunch of other heristics you can use
during training. Very often your loss
function will have very steep as a
various. So uh during training uh you
can actually end up uh overfitting. So
your training loss might just keep going
down. But then if you test the model on
other kinds of data, you might find that
after a point the error goes up. So
we uh uh typically tend to run our tests
on a validation data set and then choose
the model where
uh that gives us the lowest error on the
validation data set. Even
So uh one of the which makes you stop
your training early. So there are so you
can either track performance on the
validation set or apply one of several
early stopping criteria to terminate
training when the performance of the
valet begins to degrade. Another problem
that you often have is that the loss
function can be very steep at places and
at these places if you directly use the
derivative in your gradient descent it
can get very unstable. So you perform
something called gradient clipping where
the derivative becomes larger in
magnitude than the set value then you
clip the uh derivative value typically
to five. uh other tricks like uh
augmenting your data where you take the
same data and create many variants of to
get additional data for training and
there are other other inputs like
normalizing the input the various
initialization techniques I won't go all
over those I've gone over a little over
already but in general there's a lot to
training besides what we see in class a
lot of it is humanistics a lot of it is
sheer practice and practice makes the
person perfect so the overall
setting up of a problem. You obtain
training data, you choose a network
architecture, choose the appropriate
divergence function, the regularization,
choose your heristics, choose your
optimization algorithm. You typically
perform a grid search for
hyperparameters
and then train and evaluate periodic
periodically validation data for the
least stopping if required.
So in closing
I have outlined the process of training
networks with some history given you
some algorithms gradient descent based
techniques we've talked about
regularization and algorithms for
convergence and heristics practice makes
perfect so practice is the only you're
going to learn to get it right every
time I'll stop right here with apologies
for the break in Three.